Guide to the Gerard Gaskin photographs, 1995-2012 RL.11040
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gerard Gaskin photographs
1995-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Gaskin, Gerard, 1965-
RL.11040
2.5 Linear Feet 33 Inkjet Prints: 19 black and white, and 14 color.
This collection includes 33 photographic prints comprising the series, Legendary: Inside the House Ballroom Scene by Gerard H. Gaskin, 2012 CDS/ Honickman First Book Prize in Photography Award Winner. Prints were exhibited at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University from November 4 2013-February 22 2014.
Collection Overview
This collection includes 33 photographic prints comprising the series, Legendary: Inside the House Ballroom Scene by Gerard H. Gaskin, 2012 CDS/ Honickman First Book Prize in Photography Award Winner. Prints were exhibited at the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University from November 4 2013-February 22 2014.
About the CDS/ Honickman First Book Prize in Photography: North American photographers who are pursuing work of creative or social importance have too few opportunities for support and recognition; this is especially true when photographers are engaged in personal or in-depth ongoing projects. And while there are other sources for grants and fellowships in photography, the chance to see a body of work in print, as a coherent book-length work, is rare. Concerned about these problems and recognizing their shared organizational interests, the Honickman Foundation and the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University came together to create this important biennial book-publication prize, first awarded in 2002.
The prize is open to North American photographers who use their cameras for creative exploration, whether it be of places, people, or communities; of the natural or social world; of beauty at large or the lack of it; of objective or subjective realities. The prize honors work that is visually compelling, that bears witness, and that has integrity of purpose.
Judges for the First Book Prize in Photography are among the most significant and innovative artists, curators, and writers in contemporary photography: Robert Adams, Maria Morris Hambourg, Robert Frank, Mary Ellen Mark, William Eggleston, and Deborah Willis.
Winners of the CDS/Honickman First Book Prize in Photography receive a grant of $3,000, publication of a book of photography, published by Duke University Press and the Center for Documentary Studies, and inclusion in a website devoted to presenting the work of the prizewinners. Winners also receive a solo exhibit—beginning with the 2014 prize, at Duke University’s new Rubenstein Library Photography Gallery—after which the photographs are placed in the library’s Archive of Documentary Arts.
Deborah Willis selected Gerard H. Gaskin to win the sixth biennial competition in 2012 for his body of photographs that have been published as Legendary: Inside the House Ballroom Scene by Duke University Press and CDS Books of the Center for Documentary Studies.
Biographical / Historical
Gerard H. Gaskin, a native of Trinidad and Tobago, earned a B.A. from Hunter College in 1994. As a freelance photographer based in the greater New York City area, his work has been widely published in such publications as the New York Times, Newsday, Black Enterprise, OneWorld, Teen People, Caribbean Beat, and DownBeat; other clientele include record companies Island, Sony, Def Jam, and Mercury. His work has also been included in the books Committed to the Image: Contemporary Black Photographers (2001) and New York: A State of Mind (2000). Gaskin has received a New York Foundation for the Arts fellowship, a Center for Photography at Woodstock artist residency, and a Queens Council on the Arts Individual Artists Initiative Award. Gaskin’s photographs have been seen in solo and group exhibitions across the U.S. and abroad, including the Brooklyn Museum, Queens Museum of Art, and Black Magic Woman Festival in Amsterdam. His work is held in the permanent collections of the Museum of the City of New York and the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, among others.
Gaskin's website: http://www.gerardhgaskin.com/
More information about the CDS/Honickman First Book Prize: http://firstbookprizephoto.com/
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Gerard Gaskin Photographs were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Arrangement
Prints are unlabeled, although titles of the collection's prints were supplied by the creator. Prints have been foldered by size. Folder 1 has six 16x10" color prints. Folder 2 has six 14x22" color prints. Folder 3 has two 16x24" prints and three black and white 16x24" prints. Folders 4 and 5 have sixteen 17x26" black and white prints.
Documentary Photography -- New York; African Americans -- Pictorial works; Drag balls; Sexual minorities -- Pictorial works.; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Gaskin, Gerard, 1965-
- Joseph and Charles, POCC Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Evisu Ball, Harlem, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Latex Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- POCC Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Pargen and RR, Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Jennifer, Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- POCC Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Prodigies, Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- New York Awards Ball, Harlem, N.Y., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Ski, Xtravaganza Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Tez, Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Latex Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Vanessa, Milan Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Evisu Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Xtravaganzas, Legends Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2010 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Jlin, D.C. Awards Ball, Washington D.C., 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- RR, Ebony Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- State to State Ball, Harlem, N.Y., 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Gerald, Prada Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- New York Awards Ball, Brooklyn, N.Y., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- RR, New York Awards Ball, Brooklyn, N.Y., 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Mother’s Day Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Monica, Jay Blahnik Ball, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Gerard, Eric Bazaar Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Ebony Ball, Manhattan, N.Y., 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Karan Ball, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Mystery, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Shansee and China, Eric Bazaar Ball, Brooklyn, N.Y., 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Pony and Arturo, Jay Blahnik Ball, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- New York Awards Ball, Harlem, N.Y., 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Kelli, Legends Ball, Jersey City, N.J., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)